No, we didn't.
Oh, yes.
No, no.
No, no, no.
I don't worry about it.
It's not like that.
But I'm an obsession neurotic.
No, no. I mean, I'm
an obsession neurotic.
So I worry about others.
Do you have an alarm clock or what?
You see, this is typical of me..
I worry about other people
All the time I think I spoke
too long so I will ruin
Your child will be there alone
You will not pick him up
It will be fine
Sorry for the expression
It's necessary, exactly
You will just take some gentle things like that
Don't call me professor if you don't want me to kill you
I feel so uneasy when somebody calls me a professor.
You are a professor.
That's my problem.
I have deep problems, distrust
with any official titles and so on.
But I'm not proud of it.
It makes life difficult.
I automatically, when somebody
calls me a professor or whatever,
I take it automatically as an irony.
Oh, no, no, but it isn't, but you've earned it.
That's the thing.
It's not like the inherited title.
It's not like you're a lord or something.
Look at what Chomsky wrote about me and so on.
I was a little bit hurt.
Okay, sorry, I talk too much.
No, no, you're doing very well.
But the most obvious fact about you is
that you are not just a philosopher,
but you're a famous philosopher.
And that's kind of cool.
It's a rare thing, right?
So I'm going to ask you about the philosopher thing in a bit.
But I would like to find out what does
it mean to you that you're famous?
Is fame somehow important?
First, fame is very relative.
I have, as you know, maybe better than me, many enemies.
People who think that I'm just a clown, people
who think that beneath my amusing nature
there is some evil proto-fascist or
Stalinist whatever dimension and so on.
So I think my so-called fame
is basically just a way to keep
me at a distance, not to engage seriously with what I'm doing.
I seriously think, you know, this fame in conversation,
as far as I can guess, functions like this.
Oh, he's an interesting guy, don't take him too seriously, but
go to one of his talks, you will be amused and so on, you know.
So I'm very proud.
What I'm really proud of is that it's not limited to this.
For example, you know my crazy book, the
length of the Bible,
almost, less than nothing.
You know that it sold very well, over 10,000 in
English, in Korea it was reprinted three times.
Why?
I don't know, but it gives me hope that
nonetheless don't underestimate the public.
The publishers themselves, now they are putting pressure on
me, why don't you write a nice
bestseller on Donald Trump?
Why should I?
He's not interesting at all as a person.
He's a boring idiot and so on.
But are you worried about your books
becoming sort of coffee table books?
You know, people buy them, but they don't actually read them?
Oh, I am with, but there is a big philosophical tradition.
Now you started another topic that interests me.
You know that they are not, I wouldn't say coffee table book,
but I will characterize them as big bestsellers classics.
People buy them, nobody really reads them.
And I will give you a list.
John Rawls, a theory of justice.
I know in New York people who wrote a book on Rawls
and privately they admitted to me they didn't read the book.
And I think they are right because unfortunately Rawls,
the way he writes, you really can condense it
into like 50 pages and you don't lose a lot.
Habermas, theory of communicative action.
It's mega.
Let's go on.
He's my friend, although right-winger,
but he's provocative, I like him.
Peter Sloterdijk, his spheres.
Do you think people really read them?
And Robert Brandon, making it explicit.
All these are famous books reprinted all the time.
People don't read them.
And I have some suspicions that it's
up to a point similar even with Hegel.
phenomenology maybe, but with logic you
know I have doubts if people really read
but in a way I don't think it matters,
here is my I claim Hegelian view
did you read a wonderful book by a French author now it's translated
Pierre Bayard it's called how to talk
about books that you haven't read
and the beauty is that in the best
French style, it's not just irony.
He takes it seriously
and proves precisely
apropos of Joyce and some others that
the best books on certain authors, because
he went to check it out with authors,
I mean who wrote about this writer, are
written by guys who didn't read all of it.
He goes through sex with people who don't, sometimes,
and that's a deep dialectical Hegelian view
heaven is not a holist in the sense you have to
know all aspects, no the art of dialectics is
the right violent abstract you say
ignore all that focus on one feature
and then let this one feature color your entire approach
this is the only way to produce something really new
I claim that's the paradox of philosophies you don't have
to read it all if you know too much you just get confused.
But what about, you know, people buying
your books and perhaps not reading them,
do you nonetheless sort of see this as a good sign in the
sense that people are kind of interested in philosophy?
Yes, because nonetheless my secret hope is that there is
a certain strata of people who are looking for just jokes.
So I got some not exactly hate mail but after this series
of my latest more philosophical
books like absolute recoil
which if you ask me at a gunpoint I think
that's my sorry to say this I even find it to...
...arogan myself my best book absolute
recoil but I got head made like
where are the jokes not enough jokes and so
on yes but you know what's the secret here
I will tell you, some people who
accused me that behind my vulgar
jokes appearance is that I'm a very traditional even philosopher.
In some sense they are right and my returning to that.
Don't you see that behind all my
jokes and so on even the reason
I even use Lacanze is strictly as a means to reinterpret Hegel.
I'm very old-fashioned here.
My friend, we don't think the same, Robert Pippin,
once we talked and came to the same conclusion,
But still, it's very traditional, that still the big thing in
the history of philosophy is Kant Hegel, all these questions.
Was the movement come to think that,
legitimate, what happened with Hegel is here?
I can see that that's really interesting, especially for
someone who's also interested in the history of philosophy.
Of course, you know, at Philosophy Now we're very
interested in what philosophy can do in our time.
So what do you think philosophy can or should do
in our time, and is Hegel particularly significant?
Absolutely.
I even, to provoke my Marxist friends,
you know, although I consider myself some
kind of a Marxist, I like to say that
the thesis 11 of Feuerbach, for our time,
should be philosophers and others have tried to
change to Marxist things in the 20th century.
20th century they tried to do it.
What my friend Alain Badiou calls passion of the real.
let's really change things, the result where, to put it mildly,
Gulag, Holocaust, not exactly the best.
So maybe the time today is to not try to change
but step back and precisely to interpret the thing.
Because even at this level, would you agree with it?
I think what we need today is a
materialist reversal of Marx back to Hegel.
Hegel is, in a subtle way, much more materialist.
You know which Hegel I like?
When he says, you know, one of the most
famous passages from his philosophy of right,
the owl of Minerva takes off in the evening.
But you know that this simple sentence belies the usual claim
Hegel was a conservative who in his philosophy of right,
painted almost proto-fascist, how do you
call it, and a state, a picture of society.
So what do you think it means?
I think it means something different.
When Hegel says, a certain social order, historical orders,
can only be grasped when it's time it's over.
That's the main, no?
But do you think really Hegel was such an idiot that he didn't
know that the same was called for his philosophy of right?
The message, he doesn't bring in his philosophy
of right a system of how
our society should look.
He paints a certain work whose
time has passed, and he knew it.
But where I think Hegel is actual, so
that I don't lose my thread, is here.
Our situation is much more Hegel's than Marx's.
Marx still believed in some kind of minimal teleology.
You know, like, we are at the crucial point.
There is a chance, if not necessity, of
proletarian revolution, universal redemption.
When Hegel perceived his situation as a
post-revolutionary one, the big event happened,
the French Revolution, in some sense it went
wrong, but Hegel is here truly progressive.
The whole problem of his thought, it's not to say the French
Revolution was bullshit, let's return to the tradition,
but how to repeat it, how to keep, in spite of
some catastrophic outcomes, the legacy alive.
And I think our situation is the same.
20th century attempts at radical emancipation,
the communism we got there, they failed.
The problem is how to keep that legacy alive.
We have to abandon all that Marxist, simple
metaphoric, we are riding the train of history
and there is, you know, I always use these metaphors, ironically.
Marxists like to say even if times are dark,
we can see the light at the end of the tunnel.
And you know with which metaphor I always say,
yes, it is the light of another train coming against,
you know, so that's our situation.
And as Hegel knew it, it's open.
We cannot make any plans.
Hegel, this is very Hegelian.
But the light could be anything.
I mean, it doesn't have to be another train.
It could really be the light at the end of the tunnel, couldn't it?
Yes, but that's why the beginning is to get rid of false hopes.
Even the left today is mostly,
we have the majority, which I ironically call them this,
is still, after Fukuyama, left Fukuyamaists there most.
They basically accept liberal democracy and some
type of capitalism are the only game in town,
so let's just get it.
Better, more solidarity, healthcare,
gay marriages, whatever you want.
The big question is, then we have some, the
biggest irony of this is my answer to Fukuyama.
Once I met him, I told him this, he laughed, he
said, okay, let's say you are right, capitalism won.
But isn't the irony that today, now, the most efficient managers of
global capitalism are communists
who are still in power, you know?
So I think that we have finally to
accept that 20th century is over.
The way we did it in 20th century either social
democratic welfare state,
hardline, real socialism
or even more, that's what I hate, this type
any dreams which are coming alive now on,
some kind of non-representative direct
democracy, I don't believe in this.
Also isn't that the problem of labour, so when you say capitalism
is actually driven by communists
who are still best of mind
but there is a problem of labels
what do we mean exactly by capitalism
which takes many many forms
and of course communists
who are capitalist aren't
really communists although they are poor themselves
In what sense am I still a communist?
Just in a very limited sense
First, isn't there aren't we today
witnessing a great irony the left,
whatever remains of the left
obviously is not able to offer an
actual feasible global alternative like whenever the leftist protests
I remember when there was Occupy Wall Street
I was with them in New York, in Frankfurt
and I insisted on asking them a stupid question
What do you want?
I told them, Freud asked the wrong question
Was will das Es？
I claimed, what do you want?
What do you want?
And nobody gave me the answer
And I think that precisely because they don't know what they want,
the left takes escape into moralism, the accesses
of political correctness and so on and so on.
So my problem is this one.
On the one hand we have all these
protests, which don't have a clear idea.
On the other hand, don't we get clear signs
all around that capitalism, at least the way
we know it, is approaching an end.
Look at our...
We make we can only hope.
Look at economy, sorry, look at ecology.
It's obvious that although capitalism can do
something through taxes, regulation, it's not enough.
When there is a big catastrophe, you need larger actions.
Look at, here I agree with Fukuyama,
look at the dark potentials of biogenetics.
Our brains can already be,
and that's the philosophical problem even,
our brains can already be directly wired,
connected with the PC.
It gives us magical power.
You can really do it.
Do you know that Stephen Hawking no longer needs his finger?
He thinks forward, his wheelchair moves forward.
But at the same time, it goes the other way, right?
I think, for example, this is the thing,
the possibility of directly wiring our brain,
which will change the very basic
definition of what a human being is, maybe.
So, backwards labor, even with the labor of the human being?
With labor, you know what's the problem with the labor?
But also, I was going to ask you,
you mentioned political correctness,
which I think is a very interesting issue
so do you think...
No, sorry, just finish that
All I want to say is that
I'm sorry, I know I speak too much
we have a serious financial capital
all this fictitious capital it doesn't
help if European banks for example
are throwing hundreds of billions of
freshly printed money into the economy
most of it gets lost in fictitious capital speculations
then we have the problem of refugees and so on
We have all these problems, intellectual property,
if you ask me, capitalism is falling apart here.
Even people like, I despise them, like Mark
Zuckerberg, Elon Musk,
even they talk about it,
but you know who said the right pessimist thing
here, you must know him, it's your fellow, I mean
the German sociologist economist who is
now modest bestseller Wolfgang Streck,
he said that something totally unexpected for Marxists happens.
capitalism is clearly approaching its limit
but for marxists this always meant
there is another more progressive force waiting to take over
today capitalism is just disintegrating
you know, getting into trouble
we see that we have to improvise more and more
and already we have the first very sad consequence
as I always warn
a new figure of The ideal country is a country
that is fully integrated into the global market
but at the same time ideologically
its ethnocentric focus on its culture
Even Trump is doing this
That's why Trump gets well with all dictators
His basic deal with Saudi Arabia is
we are part of the same market,
you buy our arms, we buy your oil
It doesn't matter what you do to women there is your problem
This logic of partial cultures, China is playing this game, India,
Modi is playing this game, Putin is playing this game and so on.
So we are approaching a new world where global market will
coexist with a lack of universally accepted emancipatory rules.
This is very sad, but to go back to your question, why communism?
Because I think that all the problems that
I enumerated are the problems of commons.
Sorry, can I let you stop for one second?
Sorry, sorry, sorry.
Because I think the camera sort of keeps wobble.
I'm so sorry.
I'm sorry.
That's very fine.
Thank you, sorry.
What I want to say is, the problems...these are my beautiful dreams.
I said something too much, and then
they will jump down this, arrest us all.
You will also be arrested.
Oh, great, okay.
Let's go on.
All the problems that I enumerated, I claim, are
ultimately the problems of what Marx called commons.
Some shared substance which shouldn't
be privatized left to the markets.
Like ecology is the problem of our natural substance
to what extent we can manipulate it and so on.
Intellectual property is the problem of our intellectual substance.
Biogenetics is the problem of our substance and so on and so on.
In this sense, as I put it once, ironically, communism is
for me not a solution, but
the name of the problem today.
We will have to find a solution at that level of how to deal
with commons, with our commons outside market relations.
Even my friend who is otherwise despised
as almost neo-fascist, Peter Sloterdijk.
In a chapter of his, I don't know, he writes
even faster than me, although it's unthinkable,
I think it's what happened in the 20th century, his book.
He also comes to the same conclusion.
The era of nation states where the highest ethical value is,
are you ready to sacrifice yourself for your country, is over.
We need to make a step for, for example, just
imagine this, a friend of mine, Jean-Pierre Dupuy,
D-U-P-U-Y, maybe you should interview him, he
is a very intelligent theorist of catastrophes.
He told me that he was in Fukushima two days
after that big tsunami and then radiation.
He told me that you know for a couple of hours
the Japanese government was in total panic.
They thought that the radiation will be so strong
that they have to evacuate the entire Tokyo area.
Where would these people go?
The problem in the old days, it would be
invasion, these people invade another country.
Today you can not do it.
We need larger transnational forms of cooperation.
The only way to deal with economy,
the only way to deal with biogenetics.
If just singular states regulate it,
then Chinese, they are doing it already like crazy.
I mean, rich American, you have 20 clinics in suburbs of Shanghai,
where rich Western parents go,
and they manipulate before even it's born, the genes of Europe
All I'm saying is that I, first as a good Marxist still,
I'm absolutely not simply against capitalism.
I think capitalism, let's face it,
it's the most dynamic system in the history of humanity.
It brought incredible progress and so on.
That's why, what does this mean?
And this brings me a lot of trouble.
I'm absolutely opposed to this bullshit of relying on
local indigenous traditions to fight global capitalism.
No, we have to fight it on its own
terms with new universal global vision.
Capitalism, that's what my friends don't get it.
It began, it's very instructive to study British colonization of India.
It wasn't, you should all become like us.
It was, no, you should keep your culture.
You know that under the influence of the British colonizers,
the traditional caste system in 19th century
was even reinforced, brought to new life.
So I claim that,
and this is why, another paradoxical confusion,
who is my hero, Malcolm X, he saw it.
Malcolm X, you know what X stands for?
We were uprooted, but he saw it clearly
that this X means we have no substantial
particular way of life to which we can return.
But he saw something ingenious.
His point was so our African American,
I never liked this term because it's,
it means like Caribbean blacks can say what are
we and so on, but okay, the return is not roots.
So let's look for, it's to use this fact
that we are deprived of our ethnic substance
as a change of new, even more authentic
universality than that of mine.
So again, my point is, we have to go through capitalism.
No escape back into...
But at the same time, we have to move over,
not because I'm a utopian and want more,
but it's clear that capitalism itself is approaching a crisis
in the simple sense that the problems it
encounters today, from ecology and so on,
I am here a pessimist in the sense that capitalism
will not be over to resolve them in its own terms.
Which is why we get these paradoxes now, I didn't
forget it, I return to your question labor.
Listen, I find it so irrational that people are afraid
of robotization because it will cause unemployment.
This should be the best news that we ever heard.
Nobody says, perfect, we will have to work less.
No, the automatic assumption is a catastrophe.
We all used to think that in the 1970s we had
all these science fiction stories where all the
machines would eventually do all the work and we
would have a lot of time to control and have fun.
It can be done.
We live now in an irrational society where we are afraid of
unemployment but those who work, work more and more intensely.
I want to come back to something else because you've
taken us on a really, really interesting journey here.
So we started off with Hegel and we started
at a highly theoretical level where he talked
about philosophy in that sense and you point
us to real life problems sort of really down
to earth real problems and for me the question still
remains of what is the philosopher meant to do?
Do you look at yourself mainly as a theorist?
But you also talked about your activism.
Is there a connection between theory and practice?
You need theory to see where the activism fails.
Especially the left theory.
Isn't the whole history of the left, even in the last century,
one big history of catastrophic failures?
Which is why, as I put it somewhere ironically,
The best Marxist books were usually analyses after the effect
of why a revolution had to go wrong, Trotsky's analyses.
And isn't it sad that all we get are
excellent analyses of why we lost?
So, I would say, why philosophy?
First, because I don't trust practice.
Practice is blind without theory.
We need theory today more than ever, and by theory
I don't mean this type of direct activist theory.
Why do we need theory?
But will practice really follow out of theory?
Does that really happen, do you think?
I mean, do you think as a theorist
this is what is going to achieve?
I will be very modest here.
It's doubtful if we philosophers, I doubt it,
doubt it, will provide a new platform, political
program, but I follow here Gilles Deleuze,
otherwise I'm not a Deleuzeian, who said something that even more
important than to give the right
answers is to raise the right questions.
And here philosophy can be of some use.
We are dealing with serious problems today.
But what if we should analyse the extent to which
The very way we formulate these problems
doesn't resolve them but reproduce the problems.
And coming back to your question, that's why, for
example, I have doubts about political correctness.
Of course I agree with its goals, no
humiliation against power relations,
but you know what makes me so sad?
And here at least a little bit of philosophy enters.
think about the figure of human being that is silently presupposed by
political correctness its obsession with harassment and victimization
we are always threatened I look into your
I don't want to choose the lady eyes for
two seconds too long visual rape I was
so this division is very sad beneath it
the vision is the one of we are all
potential victims and even I think that's
true okay I don't think that's oh my
god you should visit an American campus
there and see you know what I already experienced there once I gave a speech
and a lady stood up and said I'm half black and I am
I am a single mother I have AIDS, and you are wrong.
It was so tragic that she didn't even have to go into details.
No, you had this logic of...
No, but that's abuse, isn't it?
I mean, I think on the whole, political correctness
just tells us that we should adjust our language
to the reality of the world world and the prejudices that be.
But the way it does it misfires,
because for me, the true step beyond
racism is not to change the language.
We would have to go now more into philosophy,
but even to use the same language,
but in a different, ironic, non-racist way.
Look, for example, my black friends in the United States,
they all provoke me and tell me, call me nigger.
You know what this means?
Of course I shouldn't call them nigger.
It's an empty offer.
But what they want to signal me in this way,
it's not I'm a masochist, I want to be humiliated,
But simply, we have a real contact.
I doubt if you can have a real contact with a real
person without, at least, it doesn't work always,
but as a rule, a small exchange of
obscenities or something like that.
But sorry, what I want to say, back to my basic point,
is that all these problems that we have,
even with political correctness, how language functions,
are we free or not? With digitalization, with brain science,
These are basically philosophical problems
and ordinary people will have to deal with them.
Abortion is maybe the first case of this.
Are we aware that to answer the question,
I'm sorry, don't misunderstand,
but to answer the question,
should there be abortion or not?
You have implicitly at least to
answer some philosophical question,
old values, you cannot simply say,
let's look at Christianity or whatever.
Because precisely because we are in this confused state,
where we cannot simply rely on old norms.
Like, again, something like direct link of our
brains with a computer
changes our entire pedagogy.
What does it mean to learn something，
when you just click the button and you know that.
So what I'm saying is that questions usually reserved
for philosophy will become everyday questions.
And the next thing that happens.
But it's the other way around anyway, isn't it?
I mean, everyday questions actually are with a lot of problems to take
The problem with some brain scientists and others
they think that philosophy is over
Stephen Hawking put it in one of his
last books that philosophy is dead
In some ironic sense he is not even ironic
he is right
and now we come from actual questions to my philosophical concerns
The big tragedy for me was this me was this I call it
transcendental linguistic term where all this let's call
them this way naive direct ontological
questions were prohibited were
considered naive so that all you were
allowed to do is to reflect on the
horizon of understanding or as Michel
Foucault would have put it on the
episteme, for example, if you were to ask
Michel Foucault or Foucault here, do I have
an immortal soul, since answer would have
been something like, we should analyse within
which discursive field we can even raise this
question, all you can do is just to point
out the horizon, discursive horizon within
which it's coming, and so this big naive
of the logical question what's the origin of our
universe and so on were neglected that's why i
think that natural science is entered and the
philosophical game and hawkin is right where he
said what till one 200 years ago were considered
philosophical question does the world has a
beginning or not do we have free will and so on
these are today perceived as scientific questions
Here I remain a traditional European philosopher.
I don't think philosophy disappears.
I don't think positive natural science can do the entire job.
There is still work for philosophy to do it,
but at the same time we have to break out
of this transcendental reflexive questioning
and that's the big problem.
We have to, what people like Kenton, Meyasu
and all these new materialists are doing
We have to return to big ontological questions
but in a not naive realist way
That's my problem, that's why I look into Hegel
How to move beyond the alternative between Kantian transcendentalism
things in itself are out there, we don't care about them
all we can do is our horizon of
understanding and naive realism we humans
are part of a universe a universe we are
just one of the elements no I think that
I work so hard about this specific
problems the whole first part 300 pages
of my absolute recoil works of this again how to break out of
the a transcendental horizon without falling into naive realism
Again, I think Hegel is the
way or even at this level
I see the great legacy of Christianity.
Hegel's trick is that the problem itself is its own solution.
In what sense Christianity?
What is the Christian solution?
I am an atheist incidentally.
But I see a certain legacy in
Christianity say you as a believer
feel abandoned by God what's the Christian solution it's
not oh if you work hard fast yourself
you will rejoin God no it's a much more
radical one is at that point when you
feel abandoned you identify with Christ
that you know Eli Eli Lama father why
have you forsaken me so you transpose
your division your separation from God into God
himself God on the cross is separated from himself.
It means that the very distance, the
very gap, is part of the thing itself.
And this is the formula that Hegel repeats again and again.
It's not to reach some unity above the
gap, it's to see how what you experience
as separation is a negativity
inscribed into the absolute itself.
I do very fast now.
But also if you can see that also again
following Hegel, clearly there are different
philosophical questions that come to the
fore at different times, that's very clear.
And you've given us a good idea of what kind of...
Okay, now you are silently already sharpening your knife,
because you're strike, strike, bat, go to bat, directly.
No, no, no, you've shown us what kind of approach we might take.
I was just wondering, you know, whether there's
a sort of single philosophical question that
you think is the salient question of our time.
Maybe, I will go into this, maybe it may sound
strange, but I would say the status of appearance,
because you know another way to wrap it up
in one formula, what's the greatness of Hegel
is that the usual, even for Kant, problem
is always are we limited to our constraint,
to our world of appearances, can we move beyond to reach reality
itself the way things really and Hegel, he says it somewhere
Hegel's problem is the opposite one
The true miracle, that is the miracle of negativity
How come that reality is not just flat reality
How can reality appear to itself?
Because appearance means a terrible gap
Things are not directly what they are
They appear to themselves
And now, if you dare to use it
Here I'm absolute Hegelian.
The minimum of reflectivity, appearance, is absolutely universal.
For me, now I'm jumping very fast.
The lesson of quantum physics is that appearances matter.
How you measure it, how things appear determines
what things are, and now you can use it or not.
Is that a translation problem, basically?
No, although there are translations in what sense.
One wants to be more seriously philosopher.
One has to be very precise here.
Phenomenon is not the same as Herpsheimer.
I meant in terms of language, I meant in terms of spheres.
When you are talking about the quantum level, there is a gap.
I know and I am totally opposed to those simplists who claim
who want to somehow ground the possibility of human
freedom directly into uncertainty, indeterminacy of reality
but I wasn't talking about this
all I was talking about was what really attracts me
and it's a very abstract idea philosophically in quantum physics is A
this idea of and I vary it a lot of times in my books
this idea of ontological incompleteness of reality
it's not as Lenin and naive materialist thought
reality is out there fully real we
just cannot get to know it no what if
reality in itself is in a way structured
around the gap not fully real do you
know the story I love it for your
readers maybe you know it which is my
favorite story here I found it in some
popular introduction to philosophy the
guy tries to read quantum physics based on video games you know in
In video games, when you are immersed into a
game, reality there is not fully constituted.
For example, you have a forest in the background,
if it's not part of the game that you can
go into that forest, then all the trees are not
programmed in detail, or
even most of the houses.
You just see the outside of the house, if
it's not part of the game that you enter the
house then we very well know that these
houses are within the computer program
without okay and the idea of this guy
I love it is that something why did the
TV program sorry the game programmer not
construct full reality because he would
just lose time it's meaningless why to
to why to to program the inside of a
house when it's not part of the game
that you enter it okay the idea isn't it
The most wonderfully simple one is that God
did the same when he created the universe
He stopped at the subatomic level
because he thought we humans are too stupid to progress so far
or they will not be able to move beyond atoms
so why should I bother to program velocity and position
and the idea is a very nice cynical one is that God underestimated us
we with quantum physics as it were, caught God with
his pants down, you know, ah, you were too late.
But now comes the true definition of materialism for me.
We can think this incompleteness without God.
You don't need a creator.
Just reality is incomplete.
That's one mega result, then there are many others.
So you see, I'm very careful here.
I don't try to teach one to physicists.
I just try to provide materialist, even philosophical
reading and again it all focuses on the status of appearances
So again, as Hegel says, the true problem is how appearances
emerge or as he put it, Hegel and other German idealists
The problem is not are we caught into
our subjectivity the problem is how
must reality be structured in itself
so that something like subjectivity,
subjective appearance can emerge out of it.
You know, must there be some reflexivity,
incompleteness, negativity already out there and earth?
Hegel explicitly raises this question,
that's why, that's why now comes the provocation
as they would put in the United States,
trigger warning to get it now recently a friend
of mine showed me some uh and i really mean it
i'm not denying that when i was young i didn't
watch hardcore pornography but a friend of mine
has shown me some typical hardcore heterosexual
scenes and we analyzed them and came to the point
how much more complex things are let's say this is
traditional hardcore pornography addressed at a man.
It's not true that woman is reduced to an object.
No, woman is the only subject.
Typical scene is this one.
Woman is being penetrated.
Man is reduced to pure instrument.
We find dozens of movies he found where you
don't even see man's face, he doesn't matter.
So the typical scene is this one.
Well, it's because you're taking the
perspective of the man, that's why.
No, I don't think so.
I will tell you which perspective you are taking.
Man is, you see in front, man's penis penetrating the
woman, legs spread wide, and then in the background
between her thighs, you
always see her face staring
into the camera, or at least showing her face.
So I claim you don't identify with the man.
You identify with yourself as a viewer.
What you are looking for is not your pleasure,
but the confirmation that woman enjoys.
So This is not greatest greater for women.
I claim women are in this way even more humiliated
I'm not a fan.
What I'm saying is that even here when
you think oh my god, it's just sex
Whatever the structure is that of minimal reflexivity
It doesn't if you were to show just from a close-up sex
organs penetrating each other is what could mean vulgar boring
It has to be the woman stares back and it's very humiliating for her
She has to do, I will not go into it, all the sounds and so on.
But what I'm saying is that how you see how, even in the most
immediate sexual pressure, the structure is more complicated one.
And isn't the same lesson for quantum physics that measurement
is not a measurement of some
reality which is out there.
Measurement in a way constitutes partially reality.
But how?
But measurement doesn't constitute reality, measurement
constitutes the way that we look at reality, right?
It's a little bit more radical.
Here it was a conflict between your guy, I
mean ironically, Heisenberg and Bill Bohr.
Heisenberg thought that his uncertainty
principle is only epistemological.
We cannot measure at the same time velocity and position of a particle.
Bohr criticized him, Bohr claimed, no,
this uncertainty is in the thing itself.
Particles do not have at the same time.
So the problem is that measuring the appearance,
the effect, in a way affects reality itself.
And again, the problem is how to read this in a non-idealist way.
You know, to avoid all the bullshit that,
oh, there must be a mind to construct.
Maybe it has to do with the structure of reality, but maybe also it
has to do with the expectations we have of reality, wouldn't you say?
Okay, but again, I agree with you, but I
would nonetheless add here the Hegelian point.
Don't put reality there and us here.
How is reality structured so that our
expectations of reality can influence it?
But okay, let's not loss, thank you.
You see which problems are bothering me here.
Absolutely.
Yeah, and that's why basically I'm an old-fashioned,
I'm even tempted to say old-fashioned philosopher.
I think we didn't yet really move beyond Hegel.
What happened after Hegel was different variations
of transcendentalism, even the most creative Marxism.
Therefore, we practiced transcendentalism.
Human collective praxis is the ultimate
transcendental horizon of how we perceive.
Either they are transcendentalists or
they are vulgar, naive materialists.
OK, thank you very much.
I would like to just move on so we can talk
just very briefly at least about your new books.
I've got a new book out again.
I have no idea how you do this, but...
I cheat.
I copy myself all the time.
Many of the political books...
No, no, no.
It's not like people think, do you write 20 pages per day?
My output is quite human, or to put it in ironic terms, somebody like
Sloterdijk, writes three, four times more than me.
Don't worry here.
So, now, your new book is called, and I haven't read it yet
because I haven't been able to see a copy, but it's on time.
If you want to today, I can send both of you the final proof.
You're so, so kind.
No, no, no, and I promise you something.
You will see that I have met, and I promise you if we ever meet again,
I will never ask you Did you already have the time to read it?
I hate authors who do this
Here you have my book but then you get them
Oh, did you already have a chance to read it?
Sorry, go on
We'll read it as well
So the book is called Incontinence of the
Void Economical Philosophical Spandrels
Now, okay
So I just had this short summary that I looked at
and that said that you explore the empty spaces between
philosophy, psychoanalysis and the critique of political economy
Now, to talk about spandrels...
It's a term from Steven K. Gould and so on, you know it
I'm familiar with the term, so it comes from architecture
but then finds use in evolutionary biology
But yes, so to talk about spandrels really means that
of course you have to assume the integrity of those disciplines
So if you try to find the spaces...
Here I would doubt it, why?
If you try to find the spaces then you
have to assume the arches, don't you?
I would have claimed in a Hegelian way
Sorry, can I be of any help?
You see, things always make me nervous.
My solution would have been that what if everything in order to exist
needs a spandrel, needs an empty
place which can be transformed.
In the thesis of Gould, for example, that
you don't have fully constituted organisms
and then by chance spandrels and so on.
The whole evolution, according to Gould, is based on spandrels.
You have anti-spaces, you have organs
of no use, with just like appendings.
Yes, but they are a by-product of
things that have been driven towards...
Yeah, but his idea, and he is really radical here,
is that this imbalance, in the sense that a
product never, never fully fits its function.
There is an element by-product, he goes
to the end, and the beauty of Gould,
is that he interprets accounts for human language in this way.
It's a by-product, it wasn't meant to be.
But a by-product of things that are actually driven by adaptive values,
so there are other things that have adaptive values,
so you have to assume the existence of those in order to have spandrels.
Yeah, but for him adaptation works through spandrels.
That would be my view.
Yeah, but the paradox is that the thing itself
cannot ever not even conceptually fully
function you need byproducts you need
all the time byproducts our entire human
progress but even in animal kingdom
greatness of Darwin for good is is based
in byproducts so going back to my book
what I would have said is that is that
in the same way I think that from the
very beginning that, ok, I'll put it like this, something
happens with modern philosophy, by modern
philosophy I'm old fashioned here, I mean
post-Kantian Kant and post-Kantian thoughts,
which has a privileged link with other fields,
with for example psychoanalysis.
I claimed that Freud was not simply a positive scientist and so on.
This may be the fundamental thesis of my work.
The philosophy or the philosophical stance
implied by Freud, it's not some simple naturalism
in the sense of sexuality is important and so
It's a vision of man which fits Kantian philosophy or German idealism.
So for me, my ultimate task
would be to read again German
idealism against the background of what psychoanalysis brought us.
Because psychoanalysis is a much more delicate thing.
It's not this substantialism of the unconscious,
you know, all these stupid metaphors.
conscious ego is just like the tip of the iceberg, all the dead there.
No, unconscious is purely phenomenal for Freud.
Jung has a substantial notion of the unconscious.
So
again, in one line, my program is that only by
reading psychoanalysis through German idealism
can we arrive at what psychoanalytic
revolution really amounts to, and vice versa.
Only re-read through Freud can we keep
alive the tradition of German idealism.
And I think here it's a line, I'm saying this still as a
kind of leftist Marxist, more important than Marx himself.
I think philosophically Marx following Feuerbach
and all those is a regression with regard to Hegel.
But when you ask me that, my point is this one,
now I can give you only a very condensed version.
The idea came to me and to my good friend
Jobkopjek that the structure, you know Lacan
in his Seminar 20 Encore on
feminine jouisons and some
others develops his famous or infamous formulas of situation.
He wants to account for the masculine versus feminine sexuality
through some logical paradoxes, universality with exception and so on.
And John Kovac originally came to this idea that what Lacan
is describing there, and he wasn't aware of it, I checked
with his people who knew Lacan, are the
very structures of Kantian antinomies.
Dynamic antinomies are what Lacan calls masculine,
mathematical antinomies are what Lacan calls feminine.
So of course I'm not talking about
biological sexuality, I'm talking about why
our universe, even the most abstract conceptual universe is
sexed, because of certain paradoxes of symbolisation and so on.
My second point is that this Kantian structure of antinomies
as the ultimate horizon, we cannot move beyond them.
Kant's mistake was that, as Hegel put
it in his well-known critique of Kant,
that Kant was too tender towards things.
For him, antinomies were limited to our knowledge.
Antinomies were things themselves cannot be antinomic.
Hegel's point is yes, they can.
So what I'll try to do is, through this approach, by taking
Kantian antinomies seriously in the sense of they concern
the thing itself, to read the implicit
Kantian and Hegelian than ontology
in accordance to what I improvised
that unfinished universe and so on.
It means that the world in itself is
antinomic, not fully constituted and so on.
There we have the connection with Freud,
sexuality, sexual difference and ontology.
I'm moving very fast, you may not be
convinced. I'm just giving you the outline.
My next step is an old-fashioned Marxist but it's said in Hegel's
belief that, nonetheless,
capitalism is something exceptional.
The logic of, and here we come back to your
spatulas and so on, the logic of surplus value that
we find in capitalism, where the thing cannot exist without its surplus.
What appears as a secondary surplus is the
very motive, what triggers it, and so on.
In the second part of the book, I go into detail in
detail of this parallel between
what Lacan calls surplus
enjoyment, the additional twist in enjoyment which changes simple
pleasure in what we usually call in more emphatic terms enjoyment.
And I hope some of them will be amusing numerous examples.
For example, for me, what fascinates me is, I give
you a horrible political example of enjoyment in pain.
You know, my God, you must know it, Goebbels' Totaller Creek speech.
He does something genius in a terrifying
way, Goebbels there in Palas in early 43.
All he promises to German people is more suffering.
He says, do you want a creek, a war which will be so total that
you cannot even imagine how much you will suffer
and people can...
So these paradoxes of pleasure in pain, or
what I claim is that for a certain type, I'm
now jumping just to give an idea of examples,
for a certain type of sexuality, maybe it's
Protestant sexuality, if you don't
feel guilty, you don't really enjoy it.
You have to add guilt to pleasure, to really enjoy it.
And I think all these twists of how an obstacle far from
blocking the thing, conditions it, keeps you moving.
For example, I'm sorry, this will
appear sexist, but I love the example.
A friend of mine told me this
story, maybe you even know it, how?
He told me that he had an affair with an elder lady
had a beautiful body but she the lady
told him that her last lover who saw her
naked told her that except for one or
two kilos too much she has a perfect
body and my friend made the right
reaction he told her just don't lose
that one or two kilos because the
paradox is that you have to have one or
two kilos too much in this way you create the illusion that
without those two kilos too much, your body is perfect.
But if you effectively take away one or two
kilos, you lose also the perfection, you know.
And this fundamental imbalance,
the surplus which bothers, which bothers harmony,
is the very retroactive condition of harmony.
Marx traced it, but he wasn't radical enough.
Marx's dream of of communism was
that we can get capitalist dynamics,
always more expansion, without the obstacle, without this paradox.
Okay, it's more complex.
But what I want to say is that for me,
capitalism is in this sense an ontological phenomenon.
It's the first social order, and the only in the history of humanity,
where imbalance, it's not a problem, it's a solution.
This is why always Marxists had a problem
with capitalism, they always count on crisis
but then the more capitalism is in crisis
the stronger it emerges out of it, you know.
So I deal with these ontological consequences of capitalism
and then I do something very pessimist at the end. the end.
I claim that in the classical Marxist view,
when you gather that proletarian revolutions
will not be contained in this bourgeois deadlock, you want
something, freedom, the result is catastrophic and so on, know that.
We have to accept that all revolutions, even proletarian
ones, are caught in a process that they don't dominate.
Like, you want some like October Revolution, okay we
can play this game that it was meant in a great way
but nonetheless it was a big attempt at liberation.
There are no controlled revolutions.
Sorry?
Yeah, there are no controlled revolutions.
We have to, we have to accept, it's a very Hegelian view
because you know Marx is here literally more idealist.
Marx thought, and you have this nicely done in early look-ups,
still one of the greatest books of 30th century, Geschichte
und Klassenbeburszein, Marx thought that proletarian
revolution will be a self-transparent act.
At that point of history, working class, the
subject, will know what it is doing and do it.
No, as you put it nicely, it's not
controlled, it's not self-transparent.
You have the same historical dialectic and so on.
And then I approach at the end of the book these questions
that i really like wonderful questions of
mortality in communism and although i don't like
like i fight not only against transparency
of revolutions but against these visions that
somehow in communism private life will be better
if there will be communism i claim no who knows
maybe it will be worse and so on and you know
who may take as an example i like to jump from
Sostakovich the the 14th symphony it's really
a symphony about death dying and it's so openly
brazenly pessimist etc no wonder he wasn't able
to perform it while he was still alive and so on
so again without betraying marxism i think we should
introduce this let's call
it historical density.
In all social processes, also the
progressive ones, they are non-transparent,
the result is another one and so on, which means
that fundamentally we never know what we are doing.
The act is by definition displaced, you
get something else and so on and so on.
That's actually a nice note on which to end this particular segment.
I was just going to ask you one last question so there may well
be a lot of readers or people actually see this video so they
say oh should I get turns out he's a really
interesting guy so what what should they read
you know what to recommend one of your many books
or or maybe even a book about if they have the
time the will please read philosophical stuff for
example I think I wrote a short philosophical book
on Erignis event it was translated also in german
which precisely tries to go through all the
dimensions the heideggerian event Erignis the
ultimate catastrophe Erignis end of the world
the Erignis of the fall then all the three
greatest philosophers they are for me
Plato, Descartes, Hegel why because each of them
define the whole posterity
as Michel Foucault put
it somewhere isn't the whole history of philosophy
a history of criticism of Plato and after the card
they all want to get rid of the card 19th century
they all want to get rid of Hegel how to and I
think they are all philosophers of an event
Cartesian cogito is not as he thought wrongly
thinking substance it's a pure self-relating
event of Greek the same of here so I would say
read a Reignis event if you have more energy
a little bit more read Absoluter Gegenstos the
absolute recoil please go also to these
philosophical books this is where my real work
is all the philosophical stuff like the one i just
published the courage of hopelessness and so on
listen i'm doing them with some kind of what
Sartre called movesois bad conscience you know
it's as if somebody else should be, what do I know
about society, about politics, I'm an amateur,
I always have this feeling that somebody else should have been
doing it, not me, and that I'm just feeling it for somebody else.
I feel bad with my political books.
My heart really is only in this more purely philosophical books.
Thank you very much, that's fantastic.
But now you should be a good journalist and I
will, okay, interviewer, know how I define it.
Every idiot, and I hope the two of you
are not one, can reproduce what I said.
A true journalist can do this.
You don't cheat.
You use only what I said.
But you combine it with other questions and montage
it so that you make me say a totally different thing,
but I cannot complain.
You say, fuck off, sorry
you said this and so on.
That's the challenge.
Thank you very much.
This is the challenge.
不，我们没有。
哦，是的
没有
不，不，不
我不担心
不是那样的
但我是个强迫症患者.
不，不. 我的意思是，
我是一个痴迷的神经质。
所以我担心别人.
你有闹钟吗？你看，
这就是典型的我。
我担心其他人
我总是觉得我说得太长了
所以我会耽误别人
你的孩子将独自在那里
你不会去接他 .
没事的
抱歉我的表达方式
这是必须的
你只需拿一些像这样“有礼貌”的东西.......
如果你不想让我杀了你，就不要叫我教授.
当有人叫我教授时，我感到很不安.
你就是教授。
这是我的问题
（在这方面）我问题严重，
不信任任何官方头衔。
但我并不以此为荣。
它让生活变得困难。
我会自动地...
当有人称我为教授或其他什么的时候，
我就会自动把它当成一种讽刺。
哦，不，不是这样的， 但这是你应得的。
正是如此。
它不像继承的头衔。
你又不是贵族什么的
看看乔姆斯基是怎么评价我的吧
我有点受伤了
好吧，对不起， 我说得太多了
不 不 你做得很好
但最明显的事实是，
你不仅是个哲学家
你还是个著名的哲学家
这很酷
这很难得， 对吧？
所以，我一会儿要问你 关于哲学家的事情。
但我想知道，
你的成名对你来说意味着什么？
名声在某种程度上很重要吗？
首先，名声是相对的。
我有很多敌人，你们都知道，也许比我更清楚。
有些人，认为我只是个小丑，
有些人，认为在我的逗趣天性之下
隐藏着什么邪恶的原法西斯主义
或斯大林主义等等
所以我认为，我的那些所谓的名声，
基本上只是让他人与我保持距离，
而不去真正认真对待我正在做的事情。
我确实这么认为，这种在谈话中的名声，
据我所猜测，其作用就是这样的。
哦，他是个有趣的人，别把他太当回事，
但去听他的演讲，你会被逗乐的，诸如此类。
所以我很自豪。
我真正引以为豪的是， 它不仅限于此。
比如，
你知道我那本疯狂的书--
几乎和《圣经》一样长--《少于无》
你知道这本书卖得很好，英文版销量超过
1 万册，在韩国重印了三次。
为什么？
我不知道，但这给了我希望，
不要低估了公众。
出版商自己，现在也在给我施压，
你为什么不写一本
关于唐纳德-特朗普的畅销书呢？
我为什么要写？
他这个人一点都不有趣。
他是个无聊的白痴等等。
但你担心你的书会成为
茶几上的书吗？
你知道，人们买了这些书，但实际上并没有读？
哦，我同意，但有一个很大的哲学传统。
现在你又开启了另一个我感兴趣的话题。
你知道它们不是，我不会说是咖啡桌上的书、
但我会把它们描述为大型畅销经典。
人们买它，但没人去认真地阅读它。
我会给你一份清单。
约翰-罗尔斯的《正义理论》.
我知道纽约有人写了一本关于罗尔斯的书
私下里他们向我承认，他们没有读过这本书。
我认为他们是对的，因为不幸的是，罗尔斯、
他的写作...你真的可以把它浓缩成50页左右，
而且你不会失去很多。
哈贝马斯的《沟通行动理论》.
这是一本巨著。
让我们继续.
他是我的朋友 虽然是右翼分子
但他很有煽动性 我喜欢他
彼得-斯洛特迪克，他的《领域》.
你认为人们真的会读这些书吗？
罗伯特-布兰登，《使之明确》。
这些都是再版不断的名著。
人们不会读它们。
我有些怀疑，
甚至黑格尔也有类似的地方。
《精神现象学》也许（被读过），
但《逻辑学》，我怀疑人们是否真的读过
但在某种程度上，我认为这并不重要，
这就是我自称为黑格尔的观点
你读过法国作家的一本好书吗？
皮埃尔-巴亚尔，
这本书叫《不用读完一本书》
美妙之处在于，这不仅仅是一种讽刺，
而是一种最好的法式风格。
他认真对待这个问题，
并且通过关于乔伊斯和其他一些作家的研究，
精确地证明了一个观点：
关于某些作者的最佳书籍，
是由那些并没有完全阅读其作品的人所写的。
他还特地去核实了这一点，
我是说他去查阅了那些关于这些作家的作者们的著作。
他有时会与那些不进行性活动的人发生性关系。
有时，这是一种深刻的辩证的黑格尔观点。
天堂并不是全知全能的，
你不需要了解所有方面；辩证法的艺术在于
选择正确的、激烈的抽象，
你可以忽略其他，只专注于一个特征，
然后让这个特征影响你的整个方法。
这是创造真正新事物的唯一方式。
我认为这就是哲学的悖论，你不必读完所有的哲学，
如果你知道得太多，你只会感到困惑。
但是...你知道，但是，你知道，
如果人们买了你的书，可能没有读，
你是否仍然认为这是一个好现象，
因为这表明人们对哲学有一种兴趣？
是的，因为尽管如此，我还是隐隐的认为，
有那么一部分人只想读到笑话。
所以我收到了一些邮件，虽然不算是仇恨邮件，
但在我最近出版了更具哲学性的书后，
比如《绝对反弹》——
如果你在枪口下问我，我不好意思这么说，
我甚至觉得这本书有点自负——
这是我最好的书《绝对反弹》。
但我收到的反馈是，
书中的笑话不够多，等等。
是的，但你知道秘密是什么吗？
我会告诉你，有些人指责我，
说在我粗俗笑话的外表背后，
我其实是一个非常传统的哲学家。
在某种意义上，他们是对的，我正在回归那种传统。
你没看出来吗，在我所有的笑话背后，
甚至包括我使用拉康的原因，
严格来说只是作为重新解释黑格尔的一种手段。
在这一点上，我非常守旧。
我的朋友，我们的想法不同，罗伯特·皮平，
我们曾经交谈并得出了相同的结论。
但仍然，这是非常传统的观点，
即在哲学史上重要的仍然是康德、黑格尔这些问题。
这种运动的出现是合理的吗？
黑格尔的影响何在？
我觉得这很有趣，
尤其是对于一个对哲学史也感兴趣的人来说。
当然，你知道，在《当下的哲学》杂志上，
我们非常关心哲学在我们这个时代能做什么。
那么，您认为哲学在我们这个时代能够或应该做些什么，
黑格尔是否具有特别重要的意义？
当然可以。
我甚至为了挑衅我的马克思主义朋友们，
你知道，
虽然我认为自己是某种马克思主义者，
我喜欢说，对我们这个时代而言，
费尔巴哈的第11论点应该是
哲学家和其他人试图在20世纪改变马克思主义的东西。
20 世纪，他们曾试图这样做。
我的朋友阿兰-巴迪欧称之为 "真实的激情"。
让我们真正改变事物，但结果，委婉地说，
是古拉格、大屠杀，显然不是最好的结果。
所以，也许今天我们应该做的不是试图改变，
而是退后一步，准确地解读这件事。
因为即使在这个层面上，你会同意这一点吗？
我认为，我们今天需要的是
马克思回到黑格尔的唯物主义逆转。
黑格尔以一种微妙的方式，更加唯物主义。
你知道我喜欢哪个黑格尔吗？
当他说，你知道，
在他的《法哲学原理》中最著名的一段话，
密涅瓦（智慧女神雅典娜）的猫头鹰是在黄昏时分展翅高飞。
但你知道，这句简单的话驳斥了通常的说法，
即黑格尔是一个保守主义者，
他在其《法哲学原理》中描绘了一种几乎是原始法西斯主义的，
你怎么说的，国家，一种社会形态的画面。
你认为这意味着什么？
我认为它的含义有所不同。
当黑格尔说，一个特定的社会秩序、历史秩序，
只有在它的时代结束时才能被真正理解。
这才是他的观点，不是吗？
但是你真的认为黑格尔是那么愚蠢吗，
以至于他不知道同样的命运也适用于他的《法哲学原理》吗？
在他的《法哲学原理》中
黑格尔并没有提出一个
关于我们的社会应该如何构建的系统性理论。
他描绘了一个特定的时代，一个已经过去的社会形态，
而他自己也意识到了这一点。
但我认为黑格尔在这里才是真正的黑格尔，
这样我才不会跑题。
我们的情况更接近黑格尔而非马克思。
马克思仍然相信某种最低限度的目的论。
你知道，我们正处于关键时刻。
无产阶级革命、
普遍救赎即使不是必然，也是有机会的。
当黑格尔将自己的处境视为后革命时代时，
一场大事件已经发生——
法国大革命。在某种意义上，这场革命出了问题，
但在这里黑格尔确实是进步的。
黑格尔思想的整个问题，
并不是说法国大革命是一场废话，让我们回归传统，
而是如何重复它，如何保持它的遗产活跃，
尽管有些灾难性的后果。
我想我们的情况也是一样。
20世纪对于彻底解放的尝试，
我们所经历的共产主义，它们失败了。
问题是如何让这一遗产继续传承下去。
我们必须放弃所有那些简单的马克思主义隐喻，
比如我们正在乘坐历史的列车之类的，
你知道，我总是讽刺地使用这些隐喻。
马克思主义者喜欢说，即使时代黑暗，
我们也能在隧道的尽头看到光明。
你知道我常说的比喻是什么吗？
是的，那是另一列火车迎面驶来的灯光
你知道，这就是我们的情况。
正如黑格尔所知，它是开放的。
我们无法制定任何计划。
黑格尔，这是非常黑格尔式的。
但光可能是任何东西。
我的意思是，不一定非得是另一列火车。
这真的可能是隧道尽头的曙光，不是吗？
是的，但这就是为什么一开始要摆脱虚假希望的原因。
即使是今天的左派也大多如此、
我们有大多数人，我讽刺地称他们为 "大多数人"、
在福山之后，仍以福山派居多。
他们基本上接受自由民主和
某种类型的资本主义是唯一的选择，
所以，让我们接受它吧。
更好的社会，更多的团结，医疗保健，
同性婚姻，无论你想要什么。
最大的问题是，我们有一些，
其中最大的讽刺是我对福山的回答。
有一次我见到他，我告诉他这些，他笑了，
他说，好吧，就算你是对的，资本主义赢了。
但具有讽刺意味的是，今天，现在，
全球资本主义最有效率的管理者是
那些仍在掌权的共产党人，你知道吗？
因此，我认为我们最终必须接受事实
即20 世纪已经结束了。
所以我认为我们最终必须接受20世纪已经结束了。
无论是20世纪的社会民主福利国家、
强硬的真正社会主义，
或者更甚，我所讨厌的，
任何现在开始梦想成真的类型，
比如某种非代表性的直接民主，
我对此并不信任。
确实，劳动问题是其中一部分。
当你说资本主义实际上是由
仍然是最佳思想家的共产主义者驱动时，
存在一个关于标签的问题：
我们究竟是如何准确定义资本主义的，
它有许多不同的形式。
当然，那些资本主义化的共产主义者实际上
并不是真正的共产主义者，
尽管他们自己可能很贫穷。
从什么意义上说，我还是一名共产党员？
只是在非常有限的意义上
首先，我们今天是否正在见证一个巨大的讽刺，
那就是左派——
无论左派的哪个残余部分
都显然无法提供一个真正可行的全球性替代方案，
每当左翼抗议时...
我还记得占领华尔街的时候
我和他们一起在纽约、法兰克福
我坚持要问他们一个愚蠢的问题
你想要什么？
我告诉他们，弗洛伊德问错了问题
本我想要什么（译注：可能是德语）
我说，你想要什么？
你想要什么？
没有人给我答案
我认为，这正是因为他们不知道自己想要什么、
左翼逃避道德主义、
政治正确等等，不一而足。
所以，我的问题就是如此。
一方面，我们有这么多的抗议活动，
但却没有一个明确的概念。
另一方面，我们难道
不是在四周看到了明显的迹象，
表明至少我们所知道的资本主义正在走向终结吗？
看看我们的...
我们只能寄希望于此。
看看经济，对不起，看看生态。
很显然，尽管资本主义可以通过
税收和监管做些事情，但这还不够。
当发生大灾难时，你需要更大规模的行动。
看看，这里我同意福山的观点，
看看生物遗传学的黑暗潜力。
我们的大脑已经可以
这甚至就是哲学问题、
我们的大脑已经可以被直接连接起来、
与个人电脑连接。
它赋予我们神奇的力量。
你真的可以做到。
你知道霍金不再需要他的手指了吗？
他想着向前，轮椅就向前移动。
但同时，它也会反过来，对吗？
我认为，例如，这就是问题所在，
即直接对我们的大脑进行接线的可能性，
这可能会改变
对人类本质的基本定义。
那么，逆向劳动，甚至是人类的劳动？
关于劳动，你知道劳动的问题是什么吗？
不过，我还想问你、
你提到了政治正确、
我认为这是一个非常有趣的问题
你认为...
不，对不起，我们先说完这点
我只想说
对不起，我知道我说得太多了
我们面临着严重的金融资本问题，
所有这些虚拟资本并没有帮助，
比如如果欧洲银行
向经济中投入
数千亿新印制的货币，
其中大部分资金都流失在虚拟资本的投机中。
然后我们还有难民问题等等。
我们有所有这些问题，知识产权，
如果你问我，资本主义正在这里分崩离析。
即使是像马克-扎克伯格、
埃隆-马斯克这样的人--我也鄙视他们--
甚至他们也会谈论这个话题、
但你知道谁说了正确的悲观话，
你一定认识他，是你的同伴，
德国社会学家、经济学家沃尔夫冈-施特里克，
如今已成为小有名气的畅销书作家、
他说，马克思主义者完全意想不到的事情发生了。
资本主义显然已接近其极限
但对于马克思主义者来说，这总是意味着
还有另一股更进步的力量在等待着接手
今天，资本主义正在瓦解
陷入麻烦之中
我们看到，我们必须越来越多地随机应变
我们已经有了第一个非常可悲的后果
正如我经常警告的那样，
理想国家的一个新形象是
一个完全融入全球市场的国家，
但同时在意识形态上，
它将焦点放在自己的文化上，具有民族中心主义。
就连特朗普也在这样做
这就是特朗普与所有独裁者相处融洽的原因
他与沙特阿拉伯的基本协议是
我们是同一个市场的一部分，
你们买我们的军火，我们买你们的石油
你对女人做了什么并不重要，那是你们的问题
这种局部文化的逻辑，中国在玩这个游戏，
印度莫迪也在玩这个游戏、 普京在玩这个游戏
因此，我们正在接近一个新世界，在这个世界里，
全球市场将与缺乏普遍接受的解放规则并存。
这是非常可悲的，但回到你的问题，为什么是共产主义？
因为我认为我列举的所有问题
都是公共问题。
对不起，能让你停一下吗？
对不起，对不起，对不起。
因为我觉得摄像机一直在抖。
真对不起
对不起
现在好了。
谢谢，对不起。
我想说的是，这些问题...这就是我美丽的梦想。
因为我说得太多了，
他们就会（从楼上）跳下来，把我们都抓起来。
你也会被逮捕。
太好了
我们继续。
我所列举的所有问题，我断言，
最终都是马克思所称的“共同体”问题。
一些共享的实质，
不应该被私有化留给市场。
比如生态学是我们的自然实质的问题，
我们能够操纵到什么程度。
知识产权是我们的知识实质的问题。
生物遗传学是我们的实质问题，依此类推。
从这个意义上说，正如我曾经讽刺地指出的那样，
共产主义对我来说不是一种解决方案，
而是当今问题的名称。
我们必须在这个层面上找到解决方案，
即如何在市场关系之外处理我们的公共资源。
就连我那位朋友彼得·斯劳特戴克
他在其他方面被鄙视为近乎新法西斯主义者。
在他的某一章节中，我不知道，
他写得甚至比我更快，虽然这是不可思议的，
我想这就是20世纪发生的事情，他的书
他也得出了同样的结论。
以 "你是否准备好为国牺牲
"为最高道德标准的民族国家时代已经结束。
我们需要迈出一步，例如，试想一下，
我的一位朋友让-皮埃尔-杜普伊
D-U-P-U-Y，也许你应该采访一下他，
他是一位非常聪明的灾难理论家。
他告诉我，大海啸和辐射发生两天后，
他就在福岛。
他告诉我，那几个小时中
日本政府陷入了彻底的恐慌。
他们认为辐射会非常强烈，
必须疏散整个东京地区。
这些人会去哪里？
这个问题要是放在过去，（解决方法）就是入侵，
让这些人去入侵另一个国家。
但今天，你无法这么做。
我们需要更大范围的跨国合作。
解决经济问题的唯一办法
处理生物遗传学的唯一方法。
如果只是个别国家进行管制，
那中国人，他们已经疯狂地这样做了。
我是说，在上海郊区有20家诊所，
富裕的西方父母去那里，
再婴儿出生之前对它进行调控，欧洲的基因
我想说的是，首先作为一个忠诚的马克思主义者，
我绝对不是简单地反对资本主义。
我认为资本主义，让我们面对现实吧、
这是人类历史上最具活力的系统。
它带来了令人难以置信的进步
这就是为什么，这意味着什么？
这让我很困扰。
我绝对反对这种鬼话
这种依靠本地土著传统来对抗全球资本主义的鬼话。
不，我们必须对抗它
以新的全球普遍愿景来对抗它。
资本主义，这就是我的朋友们不明白的地方。
研究英国对印度的殖民统治非常有启发性。
它并非是，你们都应该变得像我们一样。
它是，不，你应该保留你的文化。
要知道，在英国殖民者的影响下、
在 19 世纪，传统的种姓制度甚至得到了强化，
焕发出新的活力。
所以我认为
这就是为什么，又一个自相矛盾的困惑、
我的英雄马尔科姆-X，他看到了这一点。
马尔科姆-X，你知道X代表什么吗？
我们被连根拔起，但他清楚地看到，
这个X意味着
我们没有实质性的特定生活方式可以回归。
但他看到了一些独创性的东西。
他的观点是，所以我们的非裔美国人，
我从来不喜欢这个术语，因为它，
它像加勒比黑人可以说我们是什么之类的，
但好吧，归根并非返回根源。
那么，让我们寻找，利用这个事实，
即我们被剥夺了我们的民族实质，
作为一种变化，创造一种新的、
甚至比我的更真实的普遍性。
所以，我还是那句话，我们必须经历资本主义。
无法后退、逃回...
但同时，我们必须向前迈进，
不是因为我是乌托邦主义者，想要更多，
而是很明显，资本主义本身正在走向危机，
就其今天面临的问题而言，
从生态等方面来看，
在这里，我是一个悲观主义者，
因为资本主义将无法以自己的方式解决这些问题。
这就是为什么我们现在会出现这些悖论，
我没有忘记，我回到你的问题，劳动。
听着，我觉得这是非常不理性的，即
人们因为机器化会导致失业而感到害怕
这本应是我们听到的最好的消息。
（现在）没有人说，太好了，我们将不需要那么多工作了。
不，（人们都）自动的假设是一场灾难。
我们都曾在1970年代认为，
在所有这些科幻故事中，
机器最终会完成所有工作，
而我们将有大量时间来控制和享乐。
这是可以做到的。
我们现在生活在一个非理性的社会中，人们害怕失业，
但那些有工作的人工作时间越来越长，强度越来越大。
我想回到另一个话题，
因为你带我们进行了一次非常有趣的探索。
所以我们从黑格尔开始，从一个高度理论的层面开始，
他在那个意义上谈到了哲学，
而你则指向了现实生活中的问题，
非常贴近地面的真实问题。
对我来说，仍然存在的问题是，
哲学家应该做什么？
你认为自己主要是一个理论家吗？
但你也谈到了你的行动主义。
理论与实践之间有联系吗？
你需要理论来了解行动主义的失败之处。
尤其是左派理论。
左翼的整个历史，即使是在上个世纪，
不也是一部充满灾难性失败的大历史吗？
这就是为什么，正如我在某处讽刺地说，
最好的马克思主义书籍通常是事后的分析，
解释为什么革命必然会失败，例如托洛茨基的分析。
而我们得到的只是对失利原因的精彩分析，
这难道不可悲吗？
所以，我想说，为什么是哲学？
首先，因为我不相信实践。
没有理论的实践是盲目的。
我们今天比以往任何时候都更需要理论，
我所说的理论并不是指这种直接的行动主义理论。
我们为什么需要理论？
但是，理论真的能付诸实践吗？
你认为这种情况真的会发生吗？
我的意思是，作为一个理论家，
你认为这是要实现的目标吗？
在这里，我将非常谦虚。
我们哲学家是否能提供一个新的平台或政治纲领，
这是值得怀疑的，我对此表示怀疑。
但在这一点上，我跟随吉尔·德勒兹的观点，
尽管我并非德勒兹主义者。德勒兹曾说过，
比给出正确答案更重要的是
提出正确的问题。
在这里，哲学可以派上用场。
今天，我们面临着严重的问题。
但是，如果我们分析一下
我们提出这些问题的方式并没有解决这些问题，
而是再现了这些问题。
回到你的问题，这就是为什么，
比如说，我对政治正确性表示怀疑。
当然，我同意它的目标，
即反对权力关系中的羞辱，
但你知道什么让我感到如此悲哀吗？
至少在这里，哲学有一点介入。
想一想政治正确所默认的人类形象，
它对骚扰和受害者状态的迷恋，
我们总是感到受到威胁。我看着你的眼睛，
我不想过分地凝视某位女士的眼睛超过两秒，
因为这可能被视为“视觉强奸”。
这种分裂是非常悲哀的，
它背后的观点是我们都是潜在的受害者，
甚至我认为这是真的。
我不认为这是什么大不了的事——
哦，我的天，你应该去美国的校园看看。
你知道，我在那里曾经有过一次经历，我发表演讲时，
一位女士站起来说：“我是混血儿，
我是单身母亲，我有艾滋病，你说的不对。”
这太悲惨了，她甚至都不用细说。
不，你的逻辑是......
不，但这就是滥用，不是吗？
我的意思是，总的来说，
政治正确性只是告诉我们应该调整我们的语言，
以适应世界的现实和存在的偏见。
但它的做法出了问题，
因为对我来说，
真正超越种族主义的步骤不是改变语言。
我们现在需要更深入地探讨哲学，
但即使使用相同的语言，
也应该以一种不同的、讽刺的、非种族主义的方式使用。
比如，看看我在美国的黑人朋友、
他们都挑衅我，跟我说，“叫我黑鬼”。
你知道这意味着什么吗？
当然，我不应该叫他们黑鬼。
这是一个空洞的提议。
但他们想要以这种方式向我发出的信号，
并不是说“我是一个受虐狂，我想被羞辱”，
而只是表明，我们之间有了真正的接触。
我怀疑若没有至少一点点的粗话或类似的东西交流，
你是否能与一个真实的人建立真正的联系。
这不总是有效，
但通常来说是这样的。
但抱歉，我想说的是，回到我的基本观点，
即我们面临的所有这些问题，
包括政治正确性、语言如何运作、
我们是否自由、数字化、脑科学...
这些基本上都是哲学问题
而普通人将不得不面对它们。
堕胎也许是这方面的第一个案例。
我们是否意识到要回答这个问题，
我很抱歉，请不要误解，
但要回答这个问题：
应不应该有堕胎权？
至少在隐含地回答这个问题时，
你需要回答一些哲学问题，
考虑旧的价值观，你不能简单地说，
让我们看看基督教或其他什么。
因为正是因为我们处于这种混乱的状态，
在这种情况下，我们不能简单地依赖旧的规范。
就像，再次举例，
我们的大脑与计算机的直接连接
改变了我们整个的教育方法。
当你只需点击一下按钮，就知道了它的时候。
这时“学习”又意味着什么，
所以我想说的是，
通常为哲学保留的问题将变成日常问题。
接下来会发生的事情。
但无论如何，事情是反过来的，不是吗？
我的意思是，日常问题实际上充满了需要解决的问题。
一些脑科学家和其他人认为哲学已经结束了，
这就是问题所在。
斯蒂芬-霍金在其最后一本书中写道：
哲学已死
从某种讽刺的意义上说，他甚至不是在讽刺
他是对的
现在我们从实际问题转向我的哲学关注点。
对我来说，一个大悲剧是，
我称之为“超验语言学转向”，在这一转向中，
所有这些我们称之为直接本体论问题的问题被禁止，
被认为是天真的，
因此你被允许做的
只是去反思那个
被理解的视界
或者正如米歇尔·福柯所说的那样，
在认识论领域内，例如，
如果你问米歇尔·福柯，
我有不朽的灵魂吗，
他的回答可能是，
我们应该分析甚至在哪个话语领域内
我们才可以提出这个问题，
你唯一能做的就是指出它所来自的话语视界。
因此，这种大的天真的本体论问题，
比如我们的宇宙起源是什么等等，
都被忽视了。
这就是为什么我认为自然科学进入了哲学游戏，
并且霍金是正确的，
他说200年前被认为是哲学问题的问题，
比如世界是否有开始，
我们是否有自由意志等，
今天被视为科学问题。
在这里，我仍然是一位传统的欧洲哲学家。
我不认为哲学会消失。
我不认为纯粹的自然科学能够完成所有的工作。
哲学还有很多工作要做
但与此同时，
我们必须打破这种超验的反思性质疑
这才是大问题。
我们必须像肯顿、梅亚苏
和所有这些新唯物主义者所做的那样
我们必须回到本体论的大问题上来
但是是以非天真的现实主义方式
这就是我的问题，这也是为什么我研究黑格尔，
如何超越康德超验主义与天真现实主义之间的二元对立。
康德超验主义认为事物本身存在于外部，我们不关心它们，
我们所能做的只是我们的理解视界；
而天真现实主义则认为
我们人类是宇宙的一部分，
我们只是其中的一个元素。但我不这么认为。
我在这个具体问题上努力了很多，
我的《绝对反弹》一书的前300页
都在探讨这个问题，
即如何打破超验视界而不落入天真现实主义。
同样，我认为黑格尔的方法是一种方式，
甚至在这个层面上
我看到了基督教的伟大遗产。
黑格尔的诀窍在于，问题本身就是自己的解决方案。
在什么意义上的基督教？
基督教的解决方案是什么？
顺便说一句，我是一个无神论者。
但我在基督教中看到了一种特定的遗产，
比如作为一个信徒，
你感觉被上帝遗弃了，基督教的解决方案不是说，
哦，如果你努力工作、苦行自省，
你就能重新与上帝团聚，
而是一种更为激进的方式：在你感觉被遗弃的那一刻，
你要与基督产生认同，
就像你所知道的，“以利，以利，拉马撒巴克大尼？
”（父啊，父啊，为什么离弃我？）。
因此你将自己与上帝的分离转化为上帝自身的分离——
十字架上的上帝与自己分离。
这意味着，距离、差距本身
就是事物本身的一部分。
这就是黑格尔一再重复的公式。
这不是为了在差距之上达到某种统一，
而是要看到
你所经历的分离是如何成为
绝对本身中刻入的一种否定性。
我现在讲得很快。
但是，如果你能看到，
再次遵循黑格尔的思路，
很明显在不同的时期会有不同的哲学问题浮现，
这一点非常清楚。
你已经让我们很好地了解到，什么样的......
好了，现在你已经在默默磨刀了，
因为你已经开始出击、出击、击球、直接击球了。
不不不，你已经向我们展示了我们可以采取的方法。
我只是在想，你知道，
是否有一种单一的哲学问题，
你认为是我们这个时代的突出问题。
也许，我会探讨这个问题，这可能听起来有些奇怪，
但我会说是“表象的地位”，
因为另一种方式可以用一个公式来概括，
黑格尔的伟大之处在于，
通常的问题，即使对康德来说，
问题总是我们是否受限于我们的约束，
我们的表象世界，我们能否超越这些，
达到事物的真实本质。
而黑格尔的问题正好相反。
真正的奇迹，那就是否定性的奇迹。
为什么现实不仅仅是平坦的现实？
现实如何能够显现给它自己？
因为表象意味着一个可怕的鸿沟——
事物并不是直接就是它们自身，
它们要向自己显现。
现在，如果你敢于使用它，
我在这里是绝对的黑格尔主义者。
最基本的反思性、表象，是绝对普遍的。
对我来说，现在我将跳到另一个话题。
量子物理学的教训是，表象很重要。
你如何衡量它，事物的表象决定了事物的本质，
现在你可以使用它，也可以不使用它。
这基本上是一个翻译问题吗？
不是，尽管在某种意义上有翻译。
一个想要更认真地成为哲学家的人
必须在这里非常精确。
现象并不等同于Herpsheimer。
我是指在语言方面，我是指在领域方面。
当你谈论量子层面时，存在一个鸿沟。
我知道，我完全反对那些简化主义者的观点，
他们想要某种方式将人类自由的可能性
直接建立在现实的不确定性上，
但我不是在谈论这个，
我谈论的是真正吸引我的东西，
这在量子物理学中是一个非常抽象的哲学观点，
我在我的书中多次提到这个想法
这个观点是现实的本体不完整性，
它不像列宁和天真的唯物主义者所想的那样，
现实存在于外部，完全真实，
我们只是无法完全了解它。
如果现实本身以某种方式围绕着这个鸿沟构建，
不是完全真实的呢？
你知道我最喜欢的一个故事，
也许你的读者知道，
它是我最喜欢的故事
我在一本流行的哲学导论中找到的，
那个人试图基于视频游戏来解读量子物理，
你知道，在视频游戏中，当你沉浸在游戏中时，
那里的现实并没有完全构成。
例如，如果背景中有一片森林，
而这片森林不是游戏的一部分，
那么你不能进入那片森林，
其中所有的树木都没有被详细编程，
甚至大多数房屋也是如此。
如果你只看到房子的外观，
而这些房子不是游戏的一部分，你不能进入房子，
那么我们非常清楚，
这些房子在计算机程序中并没有被完全构建出来。
而这个家伙的想法，
我很喜欢，就是
为什么游戏程序员
没有构建一个完整的现实？
因为那只是浪费时间，没有意义。
当一个房子不是
你进入的游戏的一部分时
为什么要编程它的内部，是不是？
最简单而又奇妙的一个想法是，
上帝在创造宇宙时也做了同样的事情。
他在亚原子层面就停止了，
因为他认为我们人类太愚蠢，无法进展到那么远，
或者说我们无法超越原子层面。
所以为什么我还要费心去编程速度和位置呢？
这个想法是一个非常有趣的讽刺观点，即上帝低估了我们，
我们通过量子物理学，好像抓到了上帝的破绽，
你知道的，啊，你猜错了。
但现在来到了对我来说真正的唯物主义定义。
我们可以不需要上帝来思考这种不完整性。
你不需要一个创造者。
现实本身就是不完整的。
这是一个重大的结果，然后还有许多其他结果。
所以你看，我在这里非常小心。
我不试图向物理学家们传授知识。
我只是试图提供唯物主义的，甚至是哲学的解读，
而且它全部集中在表象的地位上。
再次，正如黑格尔所说，真正的问题是表象如何出现，
或者他和其他德国唯心主义者所说的，
问题不是我们是否
陷入了我们的主观性，
问题是现实本身必须如何构建，
以便能够产生像主观性、
主观表象这样的东西。
你知道，外面的世界和地球上，
是否必须存在某种反思性、不完整性和否定性呢？
黑格尔明确提出了这个问题，
这就是为什么，
这就是为什么现在来这样一个挑衅，
在美国他们会说这是触发警告，来理解它。
最近我的一个朋友给我看了一些，我真的是这么认为，
我不是在否认当我年轻时
我没有看过硬核色情，但我的一个朋友
向我展示了一些典型的硬核异性恋场景，
我们分析了这些场景，
得出了事情远比看上去复杂得多的结论，
比如说这是传统的针对男性的硬核色情，
不，女性并没有被简单地还原为一个对象。
不，女性是唯一的主体。
典型场景是这样的：
女性被侵入，
男性则被简化为纯粹的工具。
我们找到了许多电影，
在这些电影中你甚至看不到男性的脸，他并不重要。
所以典型的场景是这样的：
好吧，这是因为你采取了男性的视角，
这就是原因。
不，我不这么认为。
我会告诉你你采取了哪种视角。
你在前面看到的是男性的阴茎正在侵入女性，
女性双腿大幅度张开，
然后在她大腿之间的背景里，
你总是能看到她的脸盯着摄像机，
或至少是展示她的脸。更复杂的一个。
所以我认为你并没有与男性产生认同。
你认同的是你自己作为一个观众。
你寻找的不是你的快乐，
而是确认女性的享受。
所以这对女性来说并不是更好。
我认为这种方式甚至更加羞辱了女性，
我并不喜欢。
我想说的是，即使在这里，
当你想到，天哪，这只是性行为，
无论结构如何，那都是最低限度的反思。
如果你只展示从近景的性器官相互侵入，
这可能意味着粗俗且无聊。
必须是女性回视，这对她来说非常羞辱。
她必须做的，我不会详细讨论，所有的声音等等。
但我想说的是，你看到了，
在最直接的性压力中，结构更为复杂。
确实，
量子物理学的一个教训也是
测量并不仅仅是测量外部存在的某种现实。
在某种程度上，测量部分地构成了现实。
但是如何呢？
测量并不构成现实，
测量构成了我们观察现实的方式，对吧？
这有点更激进。
在这里，存在一个冲突，我是说，
讽刺地，介于海森堡和尼尔斯·玻尔之间。
海森堡认为他的不确定性原理
仅是认识论的。
我们不能同时测量一个粒子的速度和位置。
玻尔批评了他，玻尔声称，不，
这种不确定性存在于事物本身。
粒子在同一时间并不存在确定的状态。
因此，问题在于对表象和效果的测量
在某种程度上会影响现实本身。
问题在于如何以非唯心主义的方式解读这一点。
你知道的，避免所有的废话，
即，哦，一定有一个头脑来构建。
也许这与现实的结构有关，
但也许也与我们对现实的期望有关，你说呢？
好吧，但我还是同意你的观点，
但我还是要在这里补充黑格尔的观点。
不要把现实放在那里，而把我们放在这里。
现实是如何构成的，
以至于我们对现实的期望能够影响现实？
不过好吧，不要偏题，谢谢。
你看，哪些问题正困扰着我。
当然。
是啊，所以我基本上是个老古董、
我甚至想说老派哲学家。
我认为我们还没有真正超越黑格尔。
黑格尔之后出现的是各种不同的超验主义，
甚至是最具创造性的马克思主义。
因此，我们奉行超验主义。
人类的集体实践是，
我们如何感知的最终超越性视界。
他们要么是超验主义者，
要么是庸俗幼稚的唯物主义者。
好的，非常感谢。
我想接着说，
这样我们至少可以非常简短地谈谈您的新书。
我又出新书了。
我不知道你是怎么做到的，但是...
我作弊。
我一直在模仿自己。
许多政治书籍...
不，不，不
这不像人们想的那样，你每天写 20 页吗？
我的作品非常人性化，或者用讽刺的语言来说，就像某人
斯洛特迪克写的东西比我多三、四倍。
别担心。
现在，你的新书出版了，我还没读过，
因为我还没来得及看到它，但它已经准时出版了。
如果你们今天愿意，我可以把最终校样送给你们。
你真是太好了
不 我向你保证
你会看到我已经见过面了，如果我们再次见面，我向你保证、
我永远不会问你，你已经有时间读了吗？
我讨厌这样做的作者
给你我的书，但你会得到它们
哦，你已经读过了吗？
对不起，请继续
我们也会读的
因此，这本书的书名就叫
《虚空的失禁--经济哲学琐记》
现在，好了
因此，我只看了这个简短的摘要
也就是说，你探索了哲学，
精神分析和政治经济学批判之间的空白
现在，我们来谈谈“拱肩”...（译注：在进化生物学中，spandrel是一种表型特征，它是某些其他特征进化的副产品，而不是适应性选择的直接产物）
这是史蒂文-K-古尔德等人的术语，
我很熟悉这个词，它来自建筑学
但却在进化生物学中找到了用武之地
不过，是的，但是，谈论拱肩的确意味着
你必须假设那些学科的完整性。
所以如果你试图找到那些空间……
我对此表示怀疑，为什么？
如果你试图找到这些空间，
那么你必须假设拱门的存在，不是吗？
我会用黑格尔的方式来表述，
对不起，我能帮上什么忙吗？
你看，事情总是让我紧张。
我的解决方案是，如果
一切存在都需要一个拱肩，
需要一个可以转化的空白处。
例如，在古尔德的论文中，
你没有所谓的完整的有机体，
因为会偶然地出现拱肩之类的。
根据古尔德的说法，整个进化都是基于拱肩的。
你有反空间，你有无用的器官，
就像附属物一样。
是的，但它们是事物的副产品，
被推动向……
是的，但他的观点在这里真的很激进，
这种不平衡，意味着产品从来、
从来没有完全符合其功能。
有一个副产品元素，
他追求到底，古尔德的美在于
他以这种方式解释了人类语言。
它是一个副产品，本不应该如此。
但是一个由实际被适应性价值驱动的事物的副产品，
所以还有其他具有适应性价值的事物，
因此你必须假设这些事物的存在，以便拥有拱肩。
是的，但对他来说，适应是通过拱肩来实现的。
这就是我的看法。
是的，但矛盾在于，
事物本身永远无法完全实现功能，甚至在概念上也不行，
你需要副产品，你一直需要副产品，
我们整个人类的进步，
甚至在动物王国中，
达尔文的伟大之处也是基于副产品。
回到我的书上，
我会这样说，
我认为从一开始，
好吧，我这样说，
现代哲学发生了一些事情，
通过现代哲学我在这里有点老派，
我指的是康德后康德以及康德后思想，
它与其他领域有特殊的联系，
例如与精神分析学。
我声称，弗洛伊德不仅仅是一个实证科学家。
这可能是我工作的基本论点。
弗洛伊德所隐含的哲学或哲学立场，
并不是某种简单的自然主义，
即性是重要的。
它是一种关于人的观点，与康德哲学或德国理想主义相契合。
因此，对我来说，
我的终极任务就是在精神分析带给我们的背景下，
重新解读德国的唯心主义。
因为精神分析是一件更为微妙的事情。
它并不是潜意识的实体主义，
所有这些愚蠢的隐喻。
意识的自我只是冰山一角，所有的死亡都在那里。
不，对弗洛伊德来说，潜意识纯粹是现象性的。
荣格对潜意识有一个实体性的概念。
那么
再次强调，简单来说，我的观点是，
只有通过德国唯心主义来解读精神分析
我们才能真正理解精神分析革命的含义，
反之亦然。
只有通过重新阅读弗洛伊德，
我们才能保持德国唯心主义传统的活力。
在这里，我作为一名左翼马克思主义者，
认为这一点比马克思本人还要重要。
我认为，哲学上马克思继承了费尔巴哈等人，
相对于黑格尔而言是一种倒退。
但当你问我的时候，我的观点是这样的，
现在我只能给你一个非常简洁的版本。
这个想法是我和我的好朋友
Jobkopjek共同想到的，
拉康在他的《第二十讲座：再来一次》中
讨论了女性的享乐以及其他一些主题，
发展了他那著名或者臭名昭著的情境公式。
他希望通过一些逻辑悖论、普遍性及其例外等
来解释男性与女性的性别差异。
约翰·科瓦奇最初提出了这个想法，
即拉康在那里描述的内容，他自己并未意识到，
我向认识拉康的人确认过，
这些正是康德反经验的结构。
拉康称之为男性的是动态反经验，
他称之为女性的是数学反经验。
所以，当然，我不是在谈论生物学上的性别，
我在讨论为什么我们的宇宙，
甚至是最抽象的概念下的宇宙，是有性别的，
这是因为符号化等方面的某些悖论。
我的第二点是，这种康德式的反经验结构作为最终的视界，
我们无法超越它们。
康德的错误在于，
正如黑格尔在他对康德的著名批评中所说，
康德对事物过于温和。
对他来说，反经验仅限于我们的知识。
反经验不能是事物本身的属性。
黑格尔的观点是，它们可以是。
所以我将尝试通过这种方式，
认真对待康德的反经验，认为它们关乎事物本身，
来解读隐含的康德
和黑格尔的本体论，
这符合我即兴提出的，
未完成的宇宙等概念。
这意味着世界本身是反经验的，
没有完全构成等等。
在这里我们找到了与弗洛伊德、
性别、性别差异和本体论的联系。
我讲得很快，你可能不会被说服。
我只是给你一个大纲。
我的下一步是作为一个老派的马克思主义者，
但这是基于黑格尔的信念，
尽管如此，资本主义是某种异常现象。
这里我们回到你提到的铲子等问题，
即我们在资本主义中发现的剩余价值的逻辑，
其中事物不能没有它的剩余而存在。
看似次要的剩余实际上是驱动因素，
是触发它的东西。
在书的第二部分，
我详细讨论了拉康所称的剩余享乐与享受中
额外的扭曲之间的对应关系，
这种扭曲将简单的快乐转变为
我们通常用更强调的术语称呼的享乐。
我希望其中的一些例子会是有趣的。
例如，对我来说，让我着迷的是，
我给你们举了一个可怕的政治例子，在痛苦中享受。
你知道，我的天，你一定知道戈培尔的《全面战争演讲》。
他以一种可怕的方式做了一些天才的事，
在1943年初在柏林体育宫。
他向德国人民承诺的只有更多的苦难。
他说，你们想要一场战争吗，
一场你们无法想象将会遭受多少苦难的全面战争，
而人们可以……
因此，关于痛苦中的快乐的这些悖论，
或者我所声称的是，对于某种类型的性，
我现在跳一个话题，
为了给出一些例子，
可能是新教徒的性行为方式，
如果你不感到内疚，你就不会真正享受它。
你必须在快乐中加入负罪感，才能真正享受快乐。
我认为，所有这些曲折都说明，
障碍远非阻碍，而是条件，让你不断前进。
举个例子，很抱歉，
这会显得性别歧视，但我喜欢这个例子。
我的一个朋友告诉我这个故事，
也许你甚至知道。是怎么回事呢，
他告诉我他和一个年长的女士有过一段情事，
那位女士有一个漂亮的身体，
但她告诉他，
她的上一个情人在看到她赤裸的身体后告诉她，
除了多出的一两公斤，她的身体是完美的。
我的朋友做出了正确的反应，
他告诉她不要减掉那一两公斤，
因为悖论在于，
你必须多出那一两公斤，
这样你才能创造出一个幻觉：没有那多出的两公斤，
你的身体就是完美的。
但如果你真的减掉那一两公斤，
你也会失去那种完美
这种根本的不平衡，
这种扰乱和谐的剩余，
正是和谐的追溯性条件。
马克思意识到了这一点，但他还不够激进。
马克思对共产主义的梦想是，
我们可以获得资本主义的动态，
永远扩张，但没有障碍，没有这种悖论。
好的，这更复杂了。
但我想说的是，对我来说，
资本主义在这个意义上是一种本体现象。
它是人类历史上第一个也是唯一一个
把不平衡视为解决方案而非问题的社会秩序。
这就是为什么马克思主义者
总是对资本主义有意见，他们总是指望危机，
但是资本主义越是处于危机中，
它就越能强劲地从中崛起。
所以我处理了资本主义的这些本体论后果，
然后在最后做了一些非常悲观的事情。
我认为，在经典的马克思主义观点中，
当你认为无产阶级革命将
不会被这种资产阶级僵局所限制时，你想要的自由，
结果是灾难性的，知道这一点。
我们必须接受所有革命，甚至是无产阶级革命，
都被困在它们无法主宰的过程中。
比如，你想要像十月革命那样的革命，好吧，
我们可以玩这个游戏，它本意是伟大的，
但不管怎样，它是一次巨大的解放尝试。
没有可控的革命。
什么？
是的，没有可控的革命。
我们必须，我们必须接受，这是一种非常黑格尔式的观点，
因为你知道，马克思在这里从字面上看是更唯心主义的。
马克思认为，你可以在早期的一些资料中找到这一点，
这仍然是20世纪最伟大的书籍之一《历史和阶级意识》，
马克思认为无产阶级革命
将是一个自我透明的行动。
在那个历史时刻，工人阶级，作为主体，
将知道自己在做什么并去做它。
不，正如你很好地表达的，
它不是可控的，不是自我透明的。
你在历史辩证法中看到了相同的动态。
在书的最后，我讨论了我非常喜欢的一些问题，
关于共产主义中的死亡问题。
尽管我不喜欢，
我不仅仅是在对抗革命的透明性，
还在对抗那些以某种方式认为
在共产主义下私人生活会更好的观点。
我声称不，谁知道，也许情况会更糟。
你知道，我喜欢举例子，
我想跳到另一例子，
肖斯塔科维奇的第十四交响曲
这实际上是一部关于死亡和垂死的交响曲，
它是如此公开地、无耻地悲观，
难怪他在生前没能演出它。
所以再次说，
我认为我们应该在不背叛马克思主义的情况下
引入所谓的“历史密度”。
在所有社会过程中，
包括进步的过程，它们都是不透明的，
结果是另一个结果等等，
这意味着从根本上我们永远不知道我们在做什么。
行为本质上是被置换的，
你得到的是别的东西等等。
这实际上是结束这个特定部分的一个好注脚。
我正要问你最后一个问题，
所以可能会有很多读者或者人们实际上看到这个视频，
他们会说哦，应该去了解他，
他是一个真正有趣的人，那么他们应该读些什么呢？
你知道要推荐你的众多书籍中的哪一本，
或者如果他们有时间和意愿，
要阅读哪些哲学书籍，
比如我写过一本关于事件的短哲学书
《Erignis》（事件），它也被翻译成德语，
正是试图探讨所有维度的海德格尔事件
最终的灾难事件，
世界末日的事件，堕落的事件，
然后是三位伟大的哲学家，
对我来说他们是
柏拉图、笛卡尔、黑格尔，为什么呢？
因为他们每个人都定义了整个后代，
就像米歇尔·福柯在某处所说的，
整个哲学史难道不是对柏拉图的批评历史，
以及在笛卡尔之后，
他们都想摆脱笛卡尔，
19世纪他们都想摆脱黑格尔，如何做呢？
我认为他们都是事件的哲学家，
笛卡尔的“我思”不是他错误地认为的思维实体，
而是一种纯粹的自我关联事件，
希腊的也是如此。所以我会说
如果你有更多的精力，
稍微多读一点《绝对反弹》，
也请去读这些哲学书，
这是我的真正工作所在，
所有像我刚刚出版的
《无望的勇气》等哲学作品，
听着，当我做这些工作的时候，
我是带着某种萨特所说的坏良心做的，你知道的。
就好像应该是别人在做这件事，我对社会、
政治了解多少呢，我是个业余爱好者，
我总有种感觉应该是别人在做这件事，
而不是我，我只是在替别人填补空缺。
我对我写的政治书感到不安。
我的心真正所在的只是那些更纯粹的哲学书籍。
非常感谢，太棒了。
但现在你应该成为一个好记者，我会的，
好的，好吧，采访者，知道我是怎么定义的。
每个傻瓜，我希望你们两个不是，
都可以复述我说的话。
一个真正的记者能做到这一点。
你不作弊。
你只使用我所说的话。
但你把它与其他问题结合起来，并进行剪辑，
使得你让我说出完全不同的东西，
但我不能抱怨。
你说，滚开，虽然对不起，
但这些话确实是从你嘴里说出来的。
这就是挑战。
非常感谢。